<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Layann Wardeh - Hackers in the Bazaar Blog</title>
    <subtitle>Weekly reflections on hacker culture, open source development, and the journey through CSE 40842</subtitle>
    <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <updated>2025-11-17T22:35:59Z</updated>
    <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog</id>
    <author>
        <name>Layann Wardeh</name>
        <email>lwardeh@nd.edu</email>
    </author>

    <!-- Reading 09 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 09: Birth of Linux & Open Source Revolution</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-09"/>
        <updated>2025-11-16T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-11-16T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-09</id>
        <summary>Seventh reflection on Linus Torvalds' autobiography "Just for Fun," exploring parallels between his journey and my own path into programming, the value of building personal projects for family, and the difference between starting with a simple itch versus a grand vision.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 09: Birth of Linux & Open Source Revolution</h2>
            <p>Reading about Linus Torvalds felt surprisingly familiar and distant at the same time. I did not grow up in Finland or spend my childhood camped out in a university computer room, but I recognize parts of his story in mine. I grew up in Amman, Jordan, where it is very common for students to attend the same school from first grade until graduation. I followed that pattern at first, staying in the same school from grade 1 through 8, and then did something a little unusual for that context by switching schools for high school. That change, which might seem normal in the United States, was actually a small disruption in the usual script in Jordan, and it ended up nudging me toward a very different path.</p>

            <p>The turning point for me was the summer before my junior year, when I took my first coding class, an online Python course. Once I started coding, something clicked. I fell in love with the logic and the way a few lines of text on a screen could turn into something interactive and alive. The class had a lot of hands on projects, which made it fun rather than abstract. I remember spending hours trying to push those projects beyond what the assignment required, adding extra features and complexity, simply because I wanted to see what was possible and to learn more. <strong>No teacher asked me to do that rather it was just curiosity pulling me along.</strong> That feeling is probably the closest overlap between my story and Linus's description of happily sitting in front of a computer for hours.</p>

            <p>I found his story inspiring, especially the small personal detail about the project he made for his sister. He almost glosses over it, and if it were up to his memory alone, it might have been forgotten, but she remembered it. That stuck with me because we move through so many projects that, after a while, they blur together in our own minds. We usually remember the big ones and forget the dozens of smaller things we built along the way. <strong>It made me realize that I have not really used my skills to make something specifically for my family, even though coding and tech have become a big part of my life.</strong> There is something meaningful about using what you know to create something personal, not just something for a grade or a resume.</p>

            <p>Compared to people like Bill Gates, Steve Jobs, or Mark Zuckerberg, Linus Torvalds feels less like a distant myth and more like someone who started from a simple itch. Gates and Jobs are often framed as visionary founders and polished public figures. Zuckerberg is tied to the image of the massive social media platform and the aggressive startup culture. Linus, in contrast, started with a small, almost casual goal: <strong>make a system that worked the way he wanted, mostly for his own use and learning.</strong> The community, the impact, and the seriousness came later. That progression feels much closer to how many student projects or side projects start. You do not always launch with a grand plan. You begin with something that bothers you, and you try to fix it.</p>

            <p>Right now, my own "itch" looks much smaller from the outside, but it feels similar in spirit. For our first Hackers project, Mary, Margaret, and I worked on a game. I am still bothered that I could not get it to work exactly the way I imagined. The class moved on, and the grade is done, but the unfinished feeling has stayed with me. I keep telling myself I might revisit it over winter break and rebuild it just for fun. Whether that actually happens is still uncertain, but the fact that my mind keeps circling back to it says something about how I relate to this kind of work. I do not like letting go of a problem once I decide it should be solvable.</p>

            <p>I do not feel like I have a dramatic "nerd origin story," and maybe that is the point. I did not grow up coding from age five or taking apart machines in my bedroom. My path has been more incremental. I switched schools, took a Python class on a summer break, got hooked on the feeling of making something work, and kept choosing to come back to that space.</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Linus Torvalds"/>
        <category term="Origin Stories"/>
        <category term="Personal Projects"/>
        <category term="Jordan"/>
        <category term="Python"/>
        <category term="Curiosity"/>
        <category term="Unfinished Work"/>
        <category term="Incremental Learning"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 08 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 08: Open Source Economics</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-08"/>
        <updated>2025-11-09T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-11-09T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-08</id>
        <summary>Sixth reflection examining Eric Raymond's essays on open source economics, exploring the gift economy model, community taboos that enable coordination at scale, and the practical business models that make open source sustainable.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 08: Open Source Economics</h2>
            <p>After this week's reading, the open-source world doesn't look like chaos to me anymore. It looks like a neighborhood with unwritten rules everyone somehow knows, and a few loud neighbors who water their lawns at midnight and still get invited to the block party.</p>

            <p>What actually drives people to show up and build things for free? I don't think the answer is as mysterious as it sounds. Part of it is joy. The hands-on imperative we keep circling back to in class. You touch the thing, you change the thing, and you learn by leaving fingerprints. The other part is reputation, but ESR's "gift economy" framing clicked for me. You don't get paid in dollars up front. You get paid in trust. People start recognizing your name on a README. Your issues get a kinder reply. Later, a job or a contract shows up because your commits did the talking.</p>

            <p>ESR's "taboos" initially look conservative, pressure against forking, discouraging drive-by releases around maintainers, and the absolute rule against removing names, but mapped to throughput they make practical sense. <strong>Forks are not forbidden so much as treated as a last resort because they split attention and duplicate maintenance; bypassing maintainers might feel efficient in the moment, yet it erodes the review pipeline and raises risk; and credit stripping is simply theft, which poisons the core trade in this economy, since contributors exchange time for recognition as much as for technical progress.</strong> These norms don't contradict openness; they protect the conditions that let strangers coordinate at scale.</p>

            <p>On the money side, The Magic Cauldron basically says selling services isn't a downgrade, it's just where the real value shows up. Code wants to be copied; context doesn't. That's why people pay for the messy parts they actually feel: integrations, upgrades, SLAs, training, hosting that doesn't go down at 3 am. If the code is the tool, services are the fit and finish, and most of the pain (and budget) lives there. So it makes sense for companies to open what boosts adoption and charge for the ongoing work that keeps the thing running in real environments.</p>

            <p>Picking closed vs. open isn't a moral crusade so much as a risk call. <strong>If your edge is a tight, safety-critical algorithm with compliance or security concerns, keeping it closed can fund the rigor and reduce exposure. If your edge is ecosystem, speed, and playing nicely with others, open source is rocket fuel because it lowers the cost of trust, multiplies testers, and speeds up compatibility.</strong> Most good products split the difference: open the parts that benefit from lots of eyes, and keep the bits where secrecy still buys you time, compliance, or a real moat.</p>

            <p>If the open-source flywheel is so great, why don't more people jump in? Time pressure, not wanting to mess up in public, and a real "where do I start" problem with tools and norms. School doesn't help either. The fix isn't a pep talk; it's smaller first steps. Tighten a doc, add a test, write a minimal repro, or file a clean bug. Those are useful, low-risk, and they teach you how the project works before you try a big refactor… And taking Bui's Hackers in the Bazaar is a great first step!</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Open Source"/>
        <category term="Gift Economy"/>
        <category term="Eric Raymond"/>
        <category term="Community Norms"/>
        <category term="Business Models"/>
        <category term="Services vs Products"/>
        <category term="Getting Started"/>
        <category term="Magic Cauldron"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 06 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 06: Wealth Creation & Entrepreneurship</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-06"/>
        <updated>2025-10-12T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-10-12T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-06</id>
        <summary>Fifth reflection examining Paul Graham's perspective on startups and wealth creation, exploring the role of luck in entrepreneurial success, cultural attitudes toward risk-taking, and finding the balance between traditional career paths and entrepreneurial ambitions.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 06: Wealth Creation & Entrepreneurship</h2>
            <p>I've always wondered what it takes to found a startup, and specifically, what it takes to make it a successful one. While I think a lot of it is tied to how hard one works, how innovative the idea is, and how many people the startup serves, I do think a lot of the success comes down to luck. I listen to a podcast called "How I Built This with Guy Raz." This podcast features highly successful business owners and shares their stories of how they achieved such success. Almost all their stories are along the lines of, "I loved doing this, decided to make it a product to sell, I got really lucky, now I am a millionaire/billionaire."</p>

            <p>Looking at Paul Graham's view on startups: <strong>"Economically, you can think of a startup as a way to compress your whole working life into a few years. Instead of working at a low intensity for forty years, you work as hard as you possibly can for four. This pays especially well in technology, where you earn a premium for working fast."</strong> I think this view is a little bit misleading. While part of it is true, running a startup requires high-intensity work for some years, it doesn't come down to only four or five or six, unless your startup is extremely successful. Otherwise, you will end up having invested all your time and money without an outcome. This is where luck comes in: unless your startup came at the right time, or you were introduced to a person who took your startup to the next level, or you did the right marketing at the right time. Although this may be a pessimistic way of looking at startups, I think it holds true, especially because people always hear about the very, very low number of successful startups… but what's the number of failed startups?</p>

            <p>Growing up in Jordan, it is very common for families to just encourage their children to get a degree and then work at X company, not Twitter lol. Company X should be a decent company that pays decently well. It used to be very rare to see people go outside of the norm (degree → work) until recently. This might be true in America too, where most families encourage their children to go down the "safe" path. What I am trying to say is, before studying here, I never thought of starting my own company or even working at a startup. However, in recent years, especially during my job search, I have found that those who work at startups actually learn a lot more. They work in different parts of the business and have a huge learning curve. They also build closer relationships with those they work with. So if getting rich through joining startups is true, I wonder, why don't more people join startups? I believe, at the end of the day, it comes down to the risk involved with startups. There aren't many people who are willing to take a risk. Some are worried at the beginning of their careers that they need to start at a good company to get a good starting salary and then maybe do something out of the ordinary. Others are scared later on in their lives because they need ways to sustain themselves and their families. So there never seems to be a right time besides actually taking the first step.</p>

            <p>As someone who is interested in founding/acquiring my own company one day, I don't think there is ever a "right time." I think a lot of it comes down to taking the first step while having a backup plan, or working a job during the day and working on a separate hustle at night (my hack).</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Startups"/>
        <category term="Entrepreneurship"/>
        <category term="Risk-Taking"/>
        <category term="Wealth Creation"/>
        <category term="Paul Graham"/>
        <category term="Career Paths"/>
        <category term="Side Hustles"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 05 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 05: Programming Languages & Innovation</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-05"/>
        <updated>2025-10-05T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-10-05T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-05</id>
        <summary>Fourth reflection exploring Paul Graham's ideas on programming languages, drawing parallels between spoken languages and code, and examining how language choice shapes both thought patterns and innovation potential in software development.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 05: Programming Languages & Innovation</h2>
            <p>I found this week's readings very interesting, especially when it comes to the language a programmer uses. A lot of the emphasis was on how the programming language a programmer uses dictates the way they think and the way they solve problems. After the reading, that constraint became obvious to me, especially with the example of a programmer only using the language <strong>"Basic"</strong> and thus not knowing recursion.</p>

            <p>However, as I reflect on my experiences with programming languages, I find it difficult to find a language that I'd use that is unique to the work I would like to do. In high school, I wanted to take another AP class (to have a better-looking transcript), and the only AP that fit in my schedule was AP Computer Science A. Though that class had a prerequisite, so I had to take an online summer course to fulfill that requirement. The online class was taught in Python. Thus, the first ever language I learned was Python. Then, during the AP class, Java was taught. Finally, during my senior year, I took another programming class, which was taught in Java and we learned a bit of SQL and HTML.</p>

            <p>What I am trying to say is that during all of these courses, I was never given a chance to pick a language, rather I was given one to learn. But in addition to that, I was never taught the differences between these languages and how each language is more useful in different areas (till university at least). With that being said, I think it is similar to how babies are raised… You don't pick the language you learn as a kid, but that's what you learn, and what you become good at.</p>

            <p>Connecting back to the discussion we had in class about learning being more tailored to the individual, I wonder if there could be more opportunities (outside of this class) for students to learn a language of their choice, but with the context of these readings. If I was given the choice to learn one programming language prior to this discussion and at the very beginning of my programming journey, I would have chosen Python because of its ease of use and widespread resources. However, I wonder if providing this context to me early on would have changed my choice or if it would have encouraged me to look into the different strengths and uses of not widely used programming languages.</p>

            <p>Another interesting idea in the readings was about how businesses only excel when they are very much out of the ordinary. Interestingly, tying in how using an unconventional, powerful language is a way to <strong>"be doing something odd"</strong> that yields superior results. At first, I wanted to challenge this idea and argue that the language a programmer uses doesn't really affect the outcome. However, I thought about literature, specifically the Arabic language. In my (very humble) opinion, one of the most beautiful languages to read and one of the most descriptive languages is the Arabic language. As someone who grew up learning three languages, Arabic, English, and French, I always found that what I read in Arabic was a lot more comprehensive and rich. With this in mind, I want to go back to the idea about certain programming languages can be a driving factor in superior results and say that, yes I do agree with that. If on the literature level, different languages can have different results, then why isn't aren't different programming languages' results perceived in the same way?</p>

            <p>For this coming project, I hope I can apply the value I learned from this reading about the choice behind programming language my group chooses.</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Programming Languages"/>
        <category term="Learning Philosophy"/>
        <category term="Innovation"/>
        <category term="Multilingualism"/>
        <category term="Paul Graham"/>
        <category term="Python"/>
        <category term="Language Choice"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 03 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 03: The Sierras - The Eighties</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-03"/>
        <updated>2025-09-14T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-09-14T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-03</id>
        <summary>Third reflection on Steven Levy's Hackers, examining the "Game Hackers" era and how the introduction of commercial interests transformed the hacker ethic while questioning whether one can maintain hacker principles within a profit-driven marketplace.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 03: The Sierras - The Eighties</h2>
            <p>Reading through Part Three of <em>Hackers</em> this week, the "Game Hackers" section, really got me thinking. What struck me most was watching hacking evolve from this pure love of discovery into something tangled up with money, fame, and business ambitions. Levy describes these new hackers as people <strong>"who dreamed not only of the ultimate hack, but of fame, and big royalty checks."</strong></p>

            <p>Honestly, I can't say I was surprised by this shift. Once computers broke out of labs and garages and became something regular people could actually buy, it was pretty inevitable that someone would start thinking about markets and profit margins. But it does make you wonder, what happens to that original Hacker Ethic when the driving force isn't just curiosity anymore, but cold hard cash?</p>

            <p>When I compare these game hackers to the earlier generations, there are definitely similarities. They still had that obsessive love for computing, still pulled all-nighters perfecting their code, still got creative with solutions. But here's the key difference: their relationship with the marketplace was completely different. The earlier hackers fought against institutions and rules (and stayed away from women lol), while these Game Hackers started embracing those same systems, in some ways. Levy quotes Ken Williams as being <strong>"convinced that hackers should be stifled; what's needed is to guess what the marketplace wants, access to distribution channels, money, gimmicks, market promotion."</strong> That's so far away from Peter Samson wandering MIT's halls at 2 AM just for the pure joy of messing around with computers. It really shows how chasing commercial success can shift your priorities, even when you started with that genuine hacker spirit.</p>

            <p>There's this question Levy poses that really stuck with me: <strong>"Did you really benefit from your computer if you did not program it?"</strong> For the Game Hackers, this seemed way less important than it was for earlier generations. By the 1980s, plenty of people were getting real value from their computers without being programmers, they had games and apps that others created for them. But I think Levy's onto something here. Without being able to create or tinker with your tools, you're missing out on some of the magic that makes computing special. He also asks whether it's good for the public when one company owns a piece of software. This is where things get really interesting for me. Sure, proprietary software created stability, jobs, and gave companies reasons to keep innovating. But it also threw up walls around the things hackers cared most about: sharing knowledge, freedom to experiment, and collaboration.</p>

            <p>My takeaway? The Hacker Ethic can survive when money enters the picture, but it's going to change. While the whole ethic might not remain the same, we can definitely hold onto pieces of that spirit.</p>

            <p>For me, the sweet spot is being a professional programmer who still genuinely loves computing (probably not me being this professional, but we are talking about ideas here). You can pay your bills and still make room for that hacker perfectionism. This connects back to something we've talked about in class, whether hackers have to be full-time hackers… I really don't think so. Hackers can exist everywhere: in research labs, in politics, in game companies. What matters isn't whether they're getting paid for it, but whether they're keeping that curiosity and drive alive.</p>

            <p>So when I think about these Game Hackers, I don't see them as completely abandoning the Hacker Ethic. They were adapting it to work in a world where hacking had to pay the bills. Whether that compromise was worth it probably depends on what you value more: staying true to ideals or actually making an impact in the world. As for me? I think you can live somewhere in between. You can participate in the commercial world while still approaching your work with a hacker's mindset.</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Game Hackers"/>
        <category term="Commercialization"/>
        <category term="Hacker Ethic"/>
        <category term="Software Freedom"/>
        <category term="Professional Programming"/>
        <category term="Ken Williams"/>
        <category term="Work-Life Balance"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 02 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 02: Northern California - The Seventies</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-02"/>
        <updated>2025-09-07T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-09-07T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-02</id>
        <summary>Second reflection on Steven Levy's Hackers, exploring the connection between "True Hackers" and "Hardware Hackers," the debate over free vs. paid software, and whether hacking can be a part-time pursuit while balancing real-world responsibilities.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 02: Northern California - The Seventies</h2>
            <p>For this week's blog, I'd like to reflect on Part 2 of <em>Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</em>. As I read (listened… audible is great because there is so much to read) through these chapters, I came to the realization that "True Hackers" and the "Hardware Hackers" are not so different in their motivations, even though their approaches and communities diverged. Both groups shared a deep belief in the hands-on imperative.</p>

            <p>And this is apparent when the author wrote, <strong>"His goal was to break computers out of the protected AI towers, up from the depths of the dungeons of corporate accounting departments, and let people discover themselves by the Hands-On Imperative."</strong> What connected "True Hackers" and "Hardware Hackers" was their raw desire to explore, build, and create, while doing so for the purpose of hacking and joy of discovery rather than money or recognition. However, the difference came in how they wanted to hack. "True Hackers" wanted to stay in their labs hacking, while "Hardware Hackers" aimed to make computing accessible to everyone.</p>

            <h3>Can You Be a Part-Time Hacker?</h3>
            <p>In our class discussion, Professor Bui asked whether being a hacker means being a full-time hacker. To me, the answer is no. I don't think being a hacker requires abandoning every other pursuit in life. As the book shows, even someone like Lee had to balance passions with reality. For me, hacking can be a "part-time" job, something done alongside responsibilities.</p>

            <p>In reality, everyone needs to work to provide for their needs (at least I do), and hacking doesn't always have to replace that, but it can be done alongside providing for yourself. As I start watching <em>Mr. Robot</em> (2 weeks and still only on episode one, but progress is being made), that's exactly what the main character does: he works his day job and becomes a hacker at night. To me, this doesn't diminish his identity as a hacker, but rather reinforces that hacking can take many forms and fit into different lifestyles.</p>

            <h3>The Free vs. Paid Software Debate</h3>
            <p>Another theme that stood out was the debate about software: should it be free or paid? Fred Moore, for instance, believed in computers as tools for community, <strong>"not only for the pleasure they gave to devoted programmers, but also for their ability to bring people together."</strong> This vision of openness influenced the idea that software should be shared, not locked away.</p>

            <p>But others, like Bill Gates, rejected this notion, arguing that <strong>"software represented work, just as hardware did, and Altair BASIC was listed in the MITS catalog like anything else it sold."</strong> I think both sides have true-ness to them and can be solid arguments. However, as someone who always looks for and believes in a balance, I believe software should be both free and paid.</p>

            <h3>Finding Balance: The Freemium Model</h3>
            <p>Free versions open doors for exploration and learning, mirroring the Hacker Ethic of sharing knowledge, while paid versions, with premium features, recognize the labor and creativity of developers. And from a "business" standpoint (since my brain often wonders if I should've been a Mebroza), having a freemium version can open doors to customers to pay for the premium version since most people don't like to waste money on something if they don't know it is worth it or is what they want.</p>

            <p>However, it is important to note that some programmers create just for the joy of creating, as the book puts it, <strong>"out of sheer delight in the activity for its own sake,"</strong> like my friend H, who was mentioned in the last blog. These two ideas, creating for joy and creating for pay, I don't think contradict each other because each person will create based on their needs and interest/inspiration.</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="Hardware Hackers"/>
        <category term="Hands-On Imperative"/>
        <category term="Software Freedom"/>
        <category term="Work-Life Balance"/>
        <category term="Freemium Model"/>
        <category term="Bill Gates"/>
        <category term="Mr. Robot"/>
    </entry>

    <!-- Reading 01 Entry -->
    <entry>
        <title>Reading 01: Cambridge - The Fifties and Sixties</title>
        <link href="https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-01"/>
        <updated>2025-08-31T23:59:59Z</updated>
        <published>2025-08-31T23:59:59Z</published>
        <id>https://layannwardeh.com/blog#reading-01</id>
        <summary>First reflection on Steven Levy's exploration of early hacker culture at MIT and the origins of the hacker ethic.</summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Reading 01: Cambridge - The Fifties and Sixties</h2>
            <p>For my first blog, I'd like to start by making a comparison between the setting of the first book we are reading, <em>Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</em>, and the CSE student life at Notre Dame. Throughout reading, whenever the author mentioned Building 26 and the EAM room, I envisioned Fitzpatrick Hall of Engineering and the basement room B19, where CSE students, specifically CPEGS, spend their late nights studying.</p>
            
            <p>The author mentioned hackers working "in the basement of this building void of personality, the EAM room." The author also writes, "where [Peter] would wander the hallways at two o'clock in the morning [...] he would discover a computer that he would play with." I am not sure about you, but those lines scream Fitzpatrick ("building void of personality"), B19 room ("in the basement" and "the EAM room"), and the hallways students walk through in the middle of the night ("wander the hallways at two o'clock in the morning").</p>
            
            <h3>The Hacker Mindset: Hands-On Learning</h3>
            <p>In the early chapters, the author writes, <strong>"Peter Samson and his friends had grown up with a specific relationship to the world, wherein devices had meaning only if you found out how they worked. And how would you go about that if not by getting your hands on them?"</strong> This quote defines one of the main qualities of a hacker. It defines a hacker as someone who doesn't go about their day only experiencing it through a third-view point-of-view. Rather, a hacker goes about their day by digging deeper into the objects around them.</p>
            
            <h3>The Tension Between Academic Achievement and True Learning</h3>
            <p>Additionally, in the early chapters, the author talks about the many obstacles to learning that already exist, and mentions that to Samson, the quest of hacking meant more than a degree and more than bothering with trivial matters like teachers and grades. What set Samson apart from his peers is this carelessness he had toward his in-class education because he saw something greater, more rewarding, and with greater output.</p>
            
            <p>In my opinion, everyone is born to be a hacker in some field. It is a matter of exploring the many disciplines until finding that passion that one is born to hack in. However, if one doesn't explore enough, they won't find their passion and will end up stuck in a pursuit they like just enough that they need to make themselves great hackers at.</p>
        ]]></content>
        <category term="MIT TMRC"/>
        <category term="Hacker Origins"/>
        <category term="Notre Dame"/>
        <category term="Hands-on Learning"/>
        <category term="Academic vs. Passion"/>
        <category term="Hacker Ethic"/>
    </entry>

    
</feed>